<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Quæres concerning the state of the Church of Scotland</title>
            <author>Calderwood, David, 1575-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4362.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124661</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900327</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900327</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150819</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73631)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150819)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1982:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Quæres concerning the state of the Church of Scotland</title>
                  <author>Calderwood, David, 1575-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Holland? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Re-printed in the yeare 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By David Calderwood.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150819:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150819:1"/>
            <p>QVAERES <hi>CONCERNING</hi> The ſtate of the Church <hi>OF</hi> SCOTLAND.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEVT. 27.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Curſed be hee that maketh the blinde to goe out of the way: and all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall ſay, Amen.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Re-printed in the yeare 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="queries">
            <pb facs="tcp:150819:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150819:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Quaeres, concerning the ſtate of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Quaeres.</hi> I.</head>
            <p>WAS there ever any Realme ſince Chriſts Incarnation profeſſed Chriſtian Religion ſo univerſially through all the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, even to the utmoſt corners, in ſuch puritie both for Doctrine, Diſcipline, and publike worſhip, with ſuch libertie and for ſo many yeares together, as our Realme hath done? In the Apoſtles dayes we read not of whole Cities, let bee kingdomes, to have profeſſed the name of Chriſt. Soone after the departure of the Apoſtles, ſundrie corruptions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Church, and the myſterie of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which was working under ground in their time, was advaunced by little and little till it came to the full ripeneſſe. Neither was there any Nation free from the open profeſſion of Paganiſme the firſt 300 yeares. Since <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, that Chriſtianitie began to prevaile above Gentiliſme, there hath been no Church, which hath not beene defiled with much ſuperſtition, and corrupted with many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, till the dayes of late Reformation. From
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150819:3"/>the firſt time of reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this houre, no refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church hath ſpred it ſelf ſo univerſally through any Kingdome, with ſuch puritie of profeſſion, but either their profeſſion is not ſo univerſal, being intermingled with Papiſts, Anabaptiſts, Lutherians, or not ſo pure, as in our neighbour Church.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label>II.</label> WAS there ever any Nation which ſealed their profeſſion with Oathes, Covenants and Subſcriptions, ſo univerſallie, and ſo oft, as our Church hath done. How often hath the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, called the Kings Confeſſion, been ſubſcribed by perſons of all Eſtates through the Realme, or by particular perſons from time to time, as occaſion was offered to require their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription? A more fearfull oath cannot be concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, then is taken in the end of that Confeſſion, in theſe words: <hi>Promiſing and ſwearing by the great Name of the Lord our God, That wee ſhall continue in the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Doctrine and Diſcipline of this Church, &amp; ſhall defend the ſame according to our vocation and power, all the dayes of our lives, under the paines conteined in the Law, and danger both of Body and Soule, in the day of Gods fearefull judgement.</hi> This is the Promiſſorie oath. The Aſſertorie oath, whereupon it is grounded, is this: Wee, therefore willing to take away all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition of hyprocriſie, and of ſuch double dealing with God, and his Church, proteſt and call the <hi>Searcher of all hearts for witneſſe,</hi> That our minds and hearts doe fully agree with this our Confeſſion, Promiſe, Oath, and Subſcription. So that wee are not moved for any worldly reſpect, but are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded only in our Conſciences, through the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and love of Gods true Religion, printed in our hearts by the holy Spirit, as wee ſhall anſwer
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150819:3"/>to him in the day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall bee diſcloſed. To underlye the paines conteined in the Law, and danger both of Body and Soule in the day of Gods fearefull judgement, and to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to him in the day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall bee diſcloſed, are not lightlie to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, but to bee pondered deeplie, and ever to be remembred, ſpecially when we have to doe with this our Confeſſion.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label>III.</label> I appeale to every mans Conſcience, Whether wee have adhered to all the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall &amp; particular clauſes of this our Confeſſion, or not? When wee ſay in this Confeſſion, that wee deteſt and abhorre the Antichriſt, his five baſtard Sacraments, with all his Rites, Ceremonies, and falſe Doctrine added to the miniſtration of the true Sacraments, without the Worde of God, his cruell judgement againſt Infants departing without the Sacrament, his abſolute neceſſitie of baptizing, doe wee not proteſt that wee will abhorre and deteſt, confirmation one of the five baſtard Sacraments, kneeling, which is a Rite added to the miniſtration of the Supper, without the warrand of Gods Word, and invented by the Antichriſt, private Baptiſme, which is grounded upon the neceſſitie of baptiſme, and doubting of the Salvation of all Infants dying unbaptized; When wee proteſt wee abhorre and deteſt his dedicating of dayes, do wee not condemne obſervation of aniverſarie holy dayes? And when wee proteſt wee deteſt and abhorre not onely his owne worldly Monarchie, but alſo his wicked hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, Doe wee not condemne the degrees of Biſhops and Archbiſhops? When wee ſay, wee abhorre and deteſt all contrarie religion and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150819:4"/>(to wit, to the former Confeſſion mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned immediatelie before, and the Chriſtian faith receaved, believed, and defended by the Church of Scotland) but chieflie all kinde of Papiſtrie in generall, and particular heads, even as they are now damned and confuted by the Word of God and Kirk of Scotland. Doe wee not condemne Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Holie dayes, Kneeling, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, private Baptiſme, ſeeing all theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular heads were damned by our Church either in the former Confeſſion, the firſt or ſecond Booke of Diſcipline, and Acts of generall Aſſemblies before the ſayd Confeſſion was ſworne to and ſubſcribed, and if any preaſed to practiſe them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they were damned, the cenſures of the Church was inflicted upon them. Have wee not of late fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in all theſe particulars, and conſequentlie viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our oathes, promiſes, and ſubſcriptions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlying the danger both of body and ſoule in the day of Cods fearefull judgement, unles we repent, which wee cannot ſeriouſlie doe, except wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, ſo farre as in us lyeth, what is loſt, to the loſſe of any temporall thing whatſoever, to the ſpending of the leaſt droppe of our blood, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend what is yet reſerved whole and ſound, with the ſame hazard? For what is that hazard or loſſe in compariſon of all the paines conteined in the Law, and danger both of body and ſoule, in the day of Gods fearefull judgement. Let no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive himſelfe, thinking to deceave God with eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and ſhifts. The Searcher of all hearts knoweth what was thy meaning, when thou ſaydeſt, <hi>Wee call the Searcher of all hearts to witnes, that our mindes and hearts doe fullie agree with this our Confeſſion, Promiſe, Oath, and Subſcription:</hi> And what was the meaning
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150819:4"/>of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with which thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, thou would not uſe double dealing, was too manifeſt both in practiſe, preaching and the authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Records aboue mentioned. And put the caſe the particular heads above ſpecified, had beene a matter indifferent, howbeit they were not ſo eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by our Church, yet who can denie but thus farre at leaſt was intended to eſchew all occaſions and provocations to tyrannie, &amp; ſuperſtition, and therefore the oath, howbeit in a matter indifferent, was lawfull and ſo remaineth, as long as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine occaſions and provocations to tyrannie, and corruption, yea as long as the forbearance of them is not proved to be a ſinne. For great regard ſhould be had even to a raſh oath if it be not or proue not unlawfull, for the reverence wee ought to carrie to the <hi>great name of God.</hi> Remember of the breach of the Oath made unto the <hi>Gibeonites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <label>IIII.</label> IOyning all the three former <hi>Quaeres</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, I aſke, If ever a Realme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtian Religion ſo univerſallie, in ſuch puritie, with ſuch Libertie, for ſo many yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſealing their profeſſion with ſuch ſolemne promiſes, oathes, and ſubſcriptions (if there were any ſuch to bee found in any Hiſtorie) that did make ſuch defection, as if they did, if the heavie judgement of God did not overtake them? Or, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the conſideration of our oathes, ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſolemne Covenants, I aske, If any of the Reformed Churches in any Realme, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, profeſſing the Goſpell in the ſame puritie, and ſo many yeares, as we haue done, hath made ſo great defection as many of us haue done. Have they returned to their vomit, taken up that which they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150819:5"/>rejected &amp; condemned, remaining ſtill a reformed Church, and not overturned with force of armes? If not, then ſuppoſe wee had never ſealed our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion with ſuch ſolemne ſeales, our defection is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, and our puniſhment will bee exemplarie, unleſſe wee repent, recover what is loſt, and defend what remaineth uncorrupted.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label>V.</label> WHereunto doth this defection tend? Doth it not tend firſt to perſite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie with the Engliſh Church, then at laſt will it not ende in full conformitie with the Roman Kirk? The intent of the firſt is profeſſed by his Majeſtie in expreſſe termes extant in print: and therefore bee not deceaved with the promiſes and proteſtations of our uſurping and pretended Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats. As for example, They will ſay to you, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie careth neither for <hi>Hee Saint</hi> nor <hi>Shee Saint,</hi> but for dayes dedicat to Chriſt. They lie: For his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie obſerveth both He &amp; She Saints dayes, as well as dayes dedicat to Chriſt. So howbeit you could digeſt both a Chriſtmas Preaching and a Chriſtmas Pye, which once yee lothed, ye muſt and ſhall ere it bee long, doe as much for <hi>Saint Bartholomew, Virgin Mary,</hi> the <hi>Innocents,</hi> and all the reſt of their Saints, &amp; for five Ceremonies ye ſhall have fiftie, yea, a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. All the Relicts of Rome, which are lying like ſtincking filth in their Church, ſhall be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to us; the paterne of their Altar, their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, their Hierarchie, and Romiſh policie, ſhall bee ſet up in our Church. This defection tendeth yet further, <hi>to wit,</hi> to conformitie with Rome. What meaneth the Biſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face before his fifth Booke, to exhort his Majeſtie to proceed as hee hath alreadie begunne, to reſtore the Chriſtian Church to unitie: Papiſt, Lutherian,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150819:5"/>Formaliſt, and Calviniſt, muſt then all be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together, &amp; united in one. How, I pray you, are wee united to the Engliſh Church? Wee muſt yeeld all to them, they will not yeeld any thing at all to us, no not a hoofe, ſayd <hi>Whitgift,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terberrie,</hi> neither are they urged to yeald any thing unto us. But wee are unmercifully dealt with to yealde unto them. Shall wee for conformitie with the Lutherian the next day except of his monſtrous opinions, &amp; other fond ceremonies, after the ſame maner, and the third yeare for reconciliation with Rome, drinke of the diep of her abhomination? Or, how ſhall that great worke come to paſſe? Neither <hi>England</hi> nor <hi>Rome</hi> giveth the leaſt token of their comming towards us. Yet wee muſt play the fooles, and turne our face to them, and take our journey firſt to <hi>England,</hi> then to <hi>Rome.</hi> The Biſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> hath not ridden all the foordes of <hi>Tweed</hi> well, whatſoever is intended, this our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie will of it ſelfe tend in the end to full Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For, ſuppoſe wee ſhould give place to theſe diſturbers of our Church, who for their owne gaine and glorie, have laide aſide all reſpect to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the gaining of ſoules, and the weell of their Brethren, yet Popery ſhould increaſe more migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie, as it hath done in our neighbour Church.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label>VI.</label> WHether our conformitie end at laſt in conformitie with <hi>Rome,</hi> or not? What reaſon have wee to leave our conformitie with the pure Apoſtolicall Churches, or the beſt Reformed Churches in forraine Nations? <hi>Brightman</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth our Church, &amp; the reſt of the beſt Reformed, to the godlie Church of <hi>Philadelphia;</hi> the Engliſh to the glorious &amp; lukewarme Church of <hi>Laodicea.</hi> Shall wee caſt off our conformitie with <hi>Philadelphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150819:6"/>and conforme to <hi>Laodiceans?</hi> Is not their Church government the ſame that it was this day 100. yeares ſince in time of the groſſeſt darkeneſſe and blindneſſe, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, Chancelours, Officials, Commiſſaries, exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction in their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Courts, as they did in time of Poperie, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding both Preaching and ruling Elders from the Governement of their owne Pariſhes, and the ioynt governement of the Church, excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſuſpending, depryving, by their owne ſole authoritie, medling with Teſtamentarie, and other cauſes, not belonging to Eccleſiaſticall Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; the Biſhop taking to himſelfe the ſole admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of ſpirituall Iuriſdiction over many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth Churches; yea, deputing the ſame to Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Chancelours &amp; Officialls, and medling with the adminiſtration of Civill Affaires, as beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming his Grandeur. This Biſhop is not Pauls Biſhop, nor yet the Biſhop which was firſt erected in the Ancient Church; Hee differeth as farre from him as the Conſull in a Senate doth from a King or Monarch. So, ſeeing hee is neither the divine, nor humane Biſhop, Hee muſt bee that Satanicall, brought in by the Antichriſt. It were weariſome to goe through the calling and functions, of their Suffraganes, Deanes, Canons and Prebandaries, Organiſts, Singing boyes, Piſtlers, Goſpellers, Prieſts, Deacons, who are halfe Prieſts: their Faſts, their Eawes, their Feaſt-dayes, their Croſſing, Kneeling, Biſhopping, Houſeling of the ſicke, Baptiſme by ſuppoſition, private Baptiſme, Copes, Capes, Tipets, Surplices, Rochets, Churching of women, Marriage toyes, Funerall rittes, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150819:6"/>waried ſuperſtitiouſlie at Service, the forme of their Prayers, and the reſt of their Ceremonies. It ſufficeth, that the beſt &amp; worthieſt among them, hath continually pleaded againſt them, that they had never quyet poſſeſſion in their owne Church; that they were diſuſed in many Congregations in the latter yeares of Queen Elizabeth, of worthie memorie, till they got ſtrength againe, immediatlie after the Kings Coronation; that they are obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded onely by authoritie, not liked off by many of the Formaliſts themſelves, who doe temporiſe only, with a bad conſcience, how ſhall wee then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to a Church enthraled, and under bondage? How many times have the godlie among them put up their Prayers to God, and preferred petition to King and Parlament for the Church policie of Scotland, and the libertie of that pure Profeſſion, which we have enjoyed many yeares; and ſhall that our glorious Garland bee ſtamped underfoot? The morning clouds which eclipſed the beginning of their Reformation remaine unſcattered to this day: and ſhall they bee ſuffered to come within our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon: Not in our morning, but after many yeares, at the noone tyde of our day, to obſcure the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goſpell, which hath ſhined to us in as cleare and pure brightnes, as euer to any nation. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the charges which muſt be beſtowed upon theſe idle functions, and ſuperſtitious Ceremonies; If the Abbeyes be recovered out of Noblemens hands, I perſwade my ſelfe, they will eyther bee converted to the maintenance of Deanes, Canons and Prebendaries, Organs, Copes, and other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull uſes; or els in time bee reſtored to the olde Crowes to builde their neſts in againe.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:150819:7"/>
            <p n="7">
               <label>VII.</label> IF there were a time of Conformitie to bee graunted, which wee will never graunt; yet, is this a fit time? When the reformed Churches abroad are in ſo great hazard, and ſome preſently under the fiery tryall. When the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and all his adherents, hath reſumed freſh courage to proſecute their bloudy deſignes, hoping wholy to extirpate true Religion out of Europe; is it time to conforme to them, to take on the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of their profeſſion? Will not this encourage the enemie and diſcourage our friends?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <label>VIII.</label> IF the Antichriſtian governement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſcribed, and the many ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bee not matters of weight, but trifles; which they ſhall never bee able to prove with ſound and ſolid arguments; why are wee perſecuted for them? Is it a ſmall matter to turne a Miniſter out of his Office, wheerein hee hath ſerved many yeares, to ſend him and his familie, wife &amp; children, to begge their Bread, ſo farre as in them lyeth. For, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving dedicated themſelves to the ſervice of God, and ſpent their former time in ſtudies, they are unable to make ſhifts, as Artizans and Tradeſmen can doe. Was there ever a perſecutor ſince the dayes of Chriſt, who with one breath did both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, and pronounce the cauſe wherefore then are worſe by many degrees, then the Ethnicke, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, or Popiſh perſecutors, and conſequentlie the worſt that ever were. Our caſe is yet the more to bee pitied, that wee are denyed the protection of Law: when wee would flie to the Sanctuarie of Iuſtice, wee are ſhut backe, like unworthie beaſts,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150819:7"/>and no more pitied, then if wee were dogges, left or redelivered, into the hands of mercileſſe Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, who have given teſtimonie out of their owne mouthes, of the loyaltie, and good behaviour of thoſe whom they have perſecuted.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <label>IX.</label> AFter ſo many <hi>Quaeres,</hi> and expoſtulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in all humilitie and reverence, to the honorable, the true, and native eſtates of Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Nobles, Barronnes, and Burgeſſes: not regarding that baſtard eſtate of Prelates, I would demaund two things: Firſt, Why they ſuffer the high Commiſſion, a Court not eſtabliſhed by the Statutes of the Realme, thus to tyranniſe over the Church, over dutifull and loyall Subjects, fyning, confyning, ſuſpending, depriving, warding, and directing the Lords of Secret Counſell, to baniſh, or to give out letters of horning, againſt Miniſters, or other Profeſſors, for not conforming to Popiſh Ceremonies againſt their conſcience. The Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the higheſt Court of the Realme, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould provide that no ſtrange Court be ſet up to oppreſſe the Subjects, without their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conſent, and therefore it is, not only our <hi>Quaere,</hi> why it is not, but our requeſt, that it may bee put downe. For it is the ſtrangeſt, the moſt tyrannicall, and lawleſſe Court, that ever came in this Land, lyker to nothing, then to the Spaniſh Inquiſition, whereunto it will turne in the ende to the full, as Papiſtrie increaſeth. That one or two Archbiſhops, with two or three aſſociats, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, or civill perſons, ſuch as they pleaſe to aſſume to themſelves, being nominat in the Kings Letters Pattents, ſhould judge in all Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, and inflict both temporall and ſpirituall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150819:8"/>cenſures, and puniſhments, according to their pleaſures, is contrarie and repugnant to the word of God. For ſpirituall power, nether Princes not Parlaments, may giue to Eccleſiaſticall, or Civill perſons; nether are Eccleſiaſticall perſons capable of the power of the Temporall Sword. Seeing then, nether the one, nor the other can be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done, this high Commiſſion, ſo much grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at in our neighbour Church, ſhould not be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to have place amongſt us. Next, I demaund in all humilitie &amp; reverence, Why acts of pretended and null aſſemblies, are ratified in Parlament, and Statutes made, wherewith our pretended Prelats, make ſnares to entrap their brethren, and wherewith they countenance their tyranny? Was ever the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſemblie convocat in time of Parlament, or their advice and information ſought, ſince theſe alterations began. In England, howbeit the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats ſit in the upper Houſe as Barrons, yet they haue beſides, a convention of the Clergie, which is called the Convocation Houſe, which repreſenteth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt our generall Aſſemblie (for they have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) whoſe advyce was never neglected, no not in time of Poperie. What hath our Church deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as thus to be neglected and miſregarded, and the report, advice, conſent and wote of Prelats to bee taken, who are both judge and partie in this cauſe? The Acts of that corrupt, and pretended aſſemblie at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> were not onelie ratified, and confirmed, but alſo under name of explanation en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, and Biſhops exemed from the judgement and cenſures of the generall aſſemblie. Shall the like be done now for that pretended &amp; null Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150819:8"/>holden laſt at <hi>Perth,</hi> God forbid, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Eſtates ſhould make ſo light account of their owne credits among the Reformed Churches, to whom the proceedings of that pretended Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie are diſcovered; and if need bee, may yet bee further diſcovered: or that their Honours ſhould make light account of many faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, their owne deare Countreymen, who are reſolved, rather then to conforme, to ſuffer tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall loſſes, and to render their liues. Howbeit ſome of them have defiled themſelves with theſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, will they bee avenged on their Brethren, who for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſake have kept themſelves free, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memorie, did at the ſuit of the Commons, and upon a Bill preferred into the Houſe, at the Parlament holden the 14. yeare of her Raigne, ſignifie in expreſſe words, yet upon record, that her Will and Pleaſure was, that no Preacher or Miniſter, ſhould bee impeached, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, or otherwiſe moleſted, or troubled, for the Rites and Ceremonies in queſtion, as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble of the ſaid Bill did purport: Adding theſe comfortable words further,<note place="margin">Diall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the olde Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, &amp; now For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſt. p. <hi>54.55.</hi>
               </note> That her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, as Defender of the Faith, would ayde and maintaine all good Proteſtants to the diſcouragement of all Papiſts. Wee doe expect the like, not onely at the hands of honourable Barrons and Burgeſſes, but alſo of our Nobles, who ſhould bee nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Fathers to faithfull Subjects, but no maintainers of proud Prelats, enemies to their Eſtate, and the eſtate of Church and Countrie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
